Register of the Herbert Hoover subject collection, 1895-2006
Hoover Institution Archives
Herbert Hoover subject collection
1895-2006
62008
Hoover Institution Archives
351 manuscript boxes, 4 oversize boxes, 31 card file boxes, 2 oversize folders, 92 envelopes, 8 microfilm reels, 3 videotape cassettes, 36 phonotape reels, 31 phonorecords, memorabilia (168.2 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, printed matter, photographs, motion picture film, and sound recordings, relating to the career of Herbert Hoover as president of the United States and as relief administrator during World Wars I and II. Sound use copies of sound recordings available.
Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.
Access
Collection open for research except for Boxes 382 and 384.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1962.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Foreword
I am pleased to present to the public and to the scholarly community this detailed inventory of the Herbert Hoover Subject Collection, which are deposited in the Hoover Institution Archives at Stanford University. These papers total over 278,000 items and cover more than 75 years in the life and times of a great humanitarian and statesman.
One of Herbert Hoover's achievements was the founding in 1919 of the Hoover Institution, which became the focal point for his extensive collecting and scholarly interests. The Hoover Institution served as the only repository for his papers until 1962. At that time, the Herbert Hoover Presidential Library was created at Mr. Hoover's birthplace, West Branch, Iowa, and his presidential and certain other papers were transferred to this new repository. Nonetheless, as this published inventory reveals, many of his files (along with those of his friends and associates and the records of many organizations he served) still reside here.
In 1977, the Hoover Institution published Herbert Hoover: A Bibliography of His Writings and Addresses, which listed his numerous published works. I hope this companion volume, describing Herbert Hoover's unpublished papers and collected documents, will further facilitate the growing interest in his career and achievements among scholars and laymen alike.
W. Glenn Campbell
Director
Introduction
Between 1919, when he founded the Hoover Institution, and his death in 1964, Herbert Hoover routinely deposited papers of historical value at the Hoover Institution, including, in 1933, papers he accumulated as secretary of commerce and president of the United States. In 1962, the Department of Commerce and presidential files were transferred to the then newly established Herbert Hoover Presidential Library at West Branch, Iowa, administered by the U.S. National Archives and Records Service. When he deeded these papers to the federal government, Mr. Hoover specified that records relating to war and peace and certain other materials were to remain at the Hoover Institution. It is this latter group of materials, together with some items added after his death, that is described here.
The Herbert Hoover Collection in the Hoover Institution Archives covers the years from 1895 to 1976 and contains some 278,000 items (185 linear feet). These materials document Mr. Hoover's relief activities during and after World War I and II, his relationship with President Woodrow Wilson, his political and personal philosophy, his post-presidential career, his public service activities, and his public reputation. The principal series include a biographical file; correspondence with Woodrow Wilson; speeches and writings; articles, clippings, press summaries, and press releases about him; analyses of editorial comment published during the Hoover administration; correspondence; subject file and card file, as well as memorabilia, microfilms, motion picture films, sound recordings, and photographs. Selected materials on his service as secretary of commerce and president are also present.
The biographical series in the collection documents much of Mr. Hoover's personal and family life, including his education at Stanford University, his early business career in mining, and the honors and awards he earned. Of particular importance as a record of his daily activities are his original appointment calendars for the periods 1917-1920 and the presidential years 1929-1933 (boxes 1-2). A sizeable file of obituaries and eulogies (box 3) is also present.
The correspondence between Herbert Hoover and Woodrow Wilson constitutes a valuable part of the collection. These letters reveal major policies of the relief and conservation programs directed by Mr. Hoover during World War I, the characteristics of Wilson's administrative style, and the special relationship of trust and confidence that developed between the two men. Many of these letters were published in The Hoover-Wilson Wartime Correspondence: September 24, 1914 to November 11, 1918(Iowa State University Press, 1974) and Two Peacemakers in Paris: The Hoover-Wilson Post Armistice Letters, 1918-1920 (Texas A & M University Press, 1978), both edited by Francis William O'Brien.
The U.S. Commerce Department and presidential files consist primarily of selected copies of papers located at the Herbert Hoover Presidential Library. Some important original material is present, however, including a portion of Mr. Hoover's Commerce Department correspondence (boxes 11-12), Gen. Douglas MacArthur's report to the attorney general and other documentation on the 1932 bonus march on Washington, D. C. (boxes 23-24), material on the presidential campaigns of 1928 and 1932 (boxes 74-77), as well as a lengthy memorandum defending the Hoover administration by Edward Eyre Hunt, economic adviser to Mr. Hoover (box 73).
The series of addresses, letters, magazine articles, and press statements, commonly referred to as "the Bible," is an extensive collection of Mr. Hoover's non-book writings and addresses. A detailed calendar identifying and describing all items in this series may be consulted in the archives' reading room. The Herbert Hoover Presidential Library maintains a duplicate set of this series, together with a subject card index.
A second series of Mr. Hoover's speeches and writings contains material not in "the Bible," including printed copies of speeches, articles, and press statements, as well as original drafts of unpublished memoranda and published books. Memoranda relating to the U.S. Food Administration, the Paris Peace Conference, and relief in Europe (boxes 149-152) are of particular interest, as are those written between March and May 1933 and between September 1942 and November 1943, about critical political and international issues (box 153). This series also contains manuscript drafts and annotated galleys of several of Mr. Hoover's books, including Addresses upon the American Road; An American Epic, volumes I-IV; American Individualism; Challenge to Liberty; and Memoirs of Herbert Hoover (boxes 158-215). A published bibliography of his writings is Herbert Hoover: A Bibliography of His Writings and Addresses, compiled by Kathleen Tracey (Hoover Institution Press, 1977). Additional bibliographies are located in the biographical series (box 2).
Three series--writings about Herbert Hoover; clippings, press summaries, and press releases; and editorial analyses--provide a comprehensive record of how others saw Mr. Hoover and show the changing attitudes toward him over the years. They also give considerable information on various phases of his public career.
The correspondence series represents an uneven assortment of letters, sent and received by Mr. Hoover. Substantive matter may be found in the correspondence folders on Julius Barnes, Bernard Baruch, Hugh Gibson, James P. Goodrich, Joseph C. Grew, James A. Healy, Edward Eyre Hunt, Vernon Kellogg, John Callan O'Laughlin, John J. Pershing, Edgar Richard, H. Alexander Smith, George Sokolsky, Alonzo Taylor, Arthur H. Vandenberg, and William Allen White. The greater part of Mr. Hoover's correspondence file is located at the Herbert Hoover Presidential Library.
The subject file contains a variety of material collected by Mr. Hoover. Of particular importance are the folders on the Commission for Relief in Belgium (boxes 329-330), the American Relief Administration in Hungary and Russia (boxes 326-327), the Jewish Joint Distribution Committee, 1914-1923 (box 336), the Republican Party (box 341), the 1937 attempt to pack the Supreme Court (box 344), and Mr. Hoover's position on national defense and U.S. involvement in World War II (box 355). This series also includes writings by A. R. Lamb on the Paris Peace Conference (box 337), by Hugh Gibson on isolationism and the United Nations (box 332), and the unfinished memoirs of Edward Eyre Hunt (boxes 335-336).
Motion picture films relate primarily to his World War I relief work, his reminiscences, presidential campaigns, his presidency, reorganization of the executive department in the federal government, and his funeral and memorial services. They consist of several titled productions, as well as numerous short newsreels. Titled films include "Herbert Hoover: Master of Emergencies," "We Fed Our Enemies," "Ordeal of Wilson: A Personal Memoir," and "Washington Service for Hoover." The newsreels cover the years between 1916 and 1949, with emphasis on the 1920s.
Other audiovisual materials include photographs and sound recordings. Over 3,000 photographs from individuals, news services, and government sources depict scenes from Mr. Hoover's life. A photograph card index may be consulted in the archives' reading room. Sound recordings are present for many of Mr. Hoover's speeches and addresses, 1938-1962, and for a memorial service recorded by the National Broadcasting Corporation on October 22, 1964.
In addition to the Herbert Hoover Collection, other materials on Mr. Hoover are available for research at the Hoover Institution Archives. The Herbert Hoover Oral History Collection contains transcripts of interviews with 315 individuals who knew Mr. Hoover. Records of organizations in which Mr. Hoover played an active part, as well as papers belonging to many of his friends and associates, are accessioned as individual collections. They provide substantial documentation on international relief activities, conservation in the United States during wartime, economic organization of federal government, and other subjects. These record groups total approximately 2,100 linear feet. Together with the Herbert Hoover Collection, they constitute one of the largest bodies of materials available anywhere to the student of Herbert Hoover's life and times.
Organizations closely associated with Herbert Hoover, which have deposited archives here, include the following:
American Children's Fund, 1923-1950
Better Homes in America, 1923-1935
C.R.B. Educational Foundation, 1921-1956
Citizens Committee for the Reorganization of the Executive Branch of the Government, 1949-1958
Commission for Polish Relief, 1939-1949
Commission for Relief in Belgium, 1914-1919
Commission for Relief in Belgium, 1940
European Technical Advisers, 1919-1923
Fight for Freedom Committee, 1940-1942
Finnish Relief Fund, 1939-1946
First Aid for Hungary, 1956-1957
National Committee on Food for Small Democracies, 1940-1942
Paderewski Testimonial Fund, 1941-1959
President's Research Committee on Social Trends, 1929-1932
Red Cross. U.S. American National Red Cross, 1917-1921
Stanford University. Food Research Institute, 1919-1955
U.S. American Relief Administration, European Operations, 1919-1923
U.S. American Relief Administration, Russian Operations, 1921-1923
U.S. Commission on Organization of the Executive Branch of the Government, 1947-1949 and 1953-1955
U.S. Food Administration, 1916-1919
U.S. Fuel Administration, 1916-1919
U.S. National Industrial Conference, 1st, Washington, D.C., 1919
U.S. National Industrial Conference, 2nd, Washington, D.C., 1919-1920
U.S. President's Conference on Home Building and Home Ownership, Washington, D.C., 1931
U.S. President's Famine Emergency Committee, 1946-1947
White House Conference on Child Health and Protection, Washington, D.C., 1930
The papers of friends, associates, and relatives of Herbert Hoover are accessioned as individual collections under their own names and include the following:
Adams, Ephraim D.
Allen, Benjamin S.
Allen, Ronald
Arnold, Ralph
Axentieff, N.
Babb, Nancy
Bailey, H.S.
Baker, Elizabeth N.
Baker, George Barr
Bane, Suda L.
Barber, Alvin B.
Barker, Burt Brown
Barringer, Thomas C.
Bayne, Joseph Breckinridge
Bekeart, Laura H.
Bell, James F.
Blackwelder, Eliot
Bland, Raymond L.
Bliss, Tasker H.
Brandt, Karl
Brooks, Sidney
Brown, Everett S.
Brown, Hugh S.
Brown, Walter Lyman
Bruns, Armin R.
Burr, Myron C.
Caetani, Gelasio Benedetto Anatolio
Carroll, Philip H.
Chadbourn, Philip H. and William H.
Chatfield, Frederick H.
Childs, James R.
Christol, Carl Q.
Clark, Birge M.
Cleveland, Maude
Collins, James Hiram
Colton, Ethan T.
Cooper, Merian C.
Cotner, Robert A.
Crandall, Berton W.
Cripe, Harry E.
Crispell, Reuben B.
Curtis, Charles
Darling, Jay Norwood
Davis, Joseph S.
Dickenson, Thomas H.
Dobson, Helen Cutter
Dolan, John A.
Dyer, Susan L.
Egbert, Edward H.
Eloesser, Nina F.
Emparan, Madie Brown
Exton, Frederick
Ferriere, Suzanne
Fisher, Harold H.
Fleming, Harold M.
Fuller, Adaline W.
Fuller, W. Parmer II
Galpin, Perrin C.
Gaskill, C.A.
Gay, George I.
Gibson, Hugh
Golder, Frank A.
Goldsmith, Alan G.
Good, James W.
Goodyear, A. Conger
Green, Joseph C.
Gregory, Thomas T.C.
Gugenheim, Alice A.
Hall, Charles L.
Hall, William Chapman
Hamilton, Minard
Hartigan, John D.
Hatfield, Mark O.
Haws, R. Calvert
Healy, James A.
Henry, Charles D.
Henry, John M.
Herrington, Dorothy
Hilton, Edna M.
Hinshaw, David
Holden, Frank H.
Holman, Emile
Hoover, Hulda Randall Minthorn
Hoover, Lou Henry
Hoover, Mildred Crew Brooke
Hoover, Theodore J.
Howe, Esther B.
Hruska, Roman L.
Huber, Johann Heinrich
Hudson, Ray M.
Huenergardt, Mrs. John F.
Hunt, Edward Eyre
Hutchinson, Lincoln
Irwin, William H.
Isabelle, Reno
Jacobs, John F. de
Jacobs-Pauwels, F. Marguerite
Jessey, Joseph
Johnson, George S.
Jones, Warren Arnold
Jordan, David Starr
Kelland, Clarence B.
Kellogg, Charlotte H.
Kellogg, R. H.
Kellogg, Vernon Lyman
Kershner, Howard
Kirby, Gustavus T.
Kirwan, J.W.
Kittredge, Mabel Hyde
Kittredge, Tracy B.
Klein, Julius
Lapteff, Alexis V.
Large, Jean Henry
Leavitt, May Hoover
Lusk, Graham
Lykes, Gibbes
Lyle, Annie G.
MacLafferty, James H.
MacRae, Lillian Mae
Mason, Frank E.
McCormick, Chauncey
McLean, Hulda Brooke Hoover
McMullin, Dare Stark
Merritt, Ralph P.
Merritt, Walle W.
Miller, Bernice
Moley, Raymond
Munro, Dana C.
Murphy, Merle Farmer
Murray, Augustus T.
Myers, William Starr
Nelson, David T.
Newsom, John F.
Orbison, Thomas J.
Paradise, Scott Hurtt
Patterson, David S.
Pennington, Levi T.
Pier, H.W.
Platt, Phillip S.
Poland, William B.
Potter, Mrs. W. T.
Requa, Mark L.
Richardson, Gardner
Ringland, Arthur C.
Robinson, Henry M.
Rodgers, Marvin
Rogers, James Grafton
Rosenbluth, Robert
Russell, Tom
Sabine, Edward G.
See, Elizabeth M.
Seward, Samuel S.
Shelton, Frederick D.
Sherwell, G. Butler
Simmons, Robert G.
Slaughter, Moses Stephen
Smith, Henry B.
Smith, Robinson
Snell, Jane
Snook, Mrs. John
Snyder, Frederic S.
Sprague, Joe S.
Stader, James A.
Starr, Walter A.
Stephens, Frederick Dorsey
Stilson, Fielding J.
Stockton, Gilchrist B.
Strauss, Lewis L.
Strench, Mary Minthorn
Sullivan, Mark
Surface, Frank M.
Taylor, Alonzo E.
Terman, Lewis M.
Thane, Mrs. J.E.
Thomas, Mrs. Jerome B.
Thurston, E. Coppee
Treat, Payson J.
Tuck, William Hallam
Upman, Frank
White, William L.
White, Helen Hartley Greene
Whitlock, Brand
Wilbur, Ray Lyman
Williams, Thomas
Willis, Edward F.
Wilson, Carol Green
Withington, Robert
Wolfe, Henry C.
Work, Hubert
Znamiecki, Alexander
Zolin, Fred H.
Detailed descriptions of both the organizational records and personal papers listed above may be found in Guide to the Hoover Institution Archives (Hoover Institution Press, 1980) by Charles G. Palm and Dale Reed. These materials as well as the Herbert Hoover Collection may be examined in the archives' reading room in the Herbert Hoover Memorial Building (courtyard level) of the Hoover Institution at Stanford University. A limited number of photocopies may be purchased; a reproduction price list and policy statement are available on request. Inquiries should be addressed to the archivist.
Biographical Note
1874 Born, August 10, West Branch, Iowa
1895 A.B., Geology, Stanford University
1897-1914 International mining engineer
1899 Married Lou Henry (1874-1944)
1912-1962 Trustee, Stanford University
1914 Chairman, American Relief Committee
Received first gold medal of the Mining and Metallurgical Society of America
1914-1916 Vice-president, American Institute of Mining Engineers
1914-1920 Chairman, Commission for Relief in Belgium
1917-1920 Administrator, United States Food Administration
1918-1919 Alternating chairman, Inter-Allied Food Council
Director-general, Relief for the Allied and Associated Powers
Member, President's Committee of Economic Advisers, Paris Peace Conference
1919-1923 Director-general, American Relief Administration
1919 Founder, Hoover War Collection (later called the Hoover Institution on War, Revolution and Peace), Stanford University
1919-1920 Vice-chairman, President's Industrial Conference
1921 Member, Advisory Committee, Limitation of Armaments Conference
1921-1923 Director, Russian Famine Relief
1921-1928 Secretary of Commerce of the United States
Chairman, Colorado River Commission
1922 Chairman, President's Conference on Unemployment
1922-1925 Chairman, National Radio Conferences
1922-1926 Chairman, Annual Aviation Conferences
1922-1927 Member, World War Foreign Debt Commission
1923-1938 Chairman, Rio Grande River Commission
1924-1928 Member, Federal Oil Conservation Board
1924-1928 Chairman, Committee on Coordination of Rail and Water Facilities
Chairman, National Conferences on Street and Highway Safety
Chairman, St. Lawrence Waterway Commission
1926 Member, Cabinet Committee on Reorganization of Government Departments
1927 Director, Mississippi Flood Relief
1929-1933 President of the United States
1936-1964 Chairman, Boys' Clubs of America
1939-1940 Founder, Finnish Relief Fund
1940-1942 Chairman, Committee on Food for the Small Democracies
1946 Initiator (through General William H. Haskell), CARE
1946-1947 Cofounder, UNICEF
Coordinator, food supply for thirty-eight nations in the world famine of 1946-1947
1947 Head, special mission to investigate the economy of Germany and Austria at the request of President Truman
1947-1949 Chairman, Commission on Organization of the Executive Branch of the Government
1953-1955 Chairman, Commission on Organization of the Executive Branch of the Government
1954 Chairman, mission to Germany at the request of President Eisenhower and Chancellor Adenauer
1956-1957 Honorary chairman, First Aid to Hungary
1958 United States Representative, World's Fair, Brussels
1962 Recipient of gold medal, Stanford University, fifty years as Trustee
1964 Unanimous Resolution of Appreciation, United States Congress (third such resolution during his lifetime)
Died, October 20, New York City
Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; International relief.; Moving-pictures.; Phonorecords.; Phonotapes.; United States--Politics and government--1929-1933.; United States--Politics and government--20th century.; Video tapes.; World War, 1914-1918--Civilian relief.; World War, 1939-1945--Civilian relief.
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1895-1971 (Box 1-5)
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical writings, memorabilia, correspondence, appointment calendars, and printed matter relating to the life of Herbert Hoover, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Address books, Typescript., n.d. (Box 1)
  - Appointment calendars, arranged chronologically.
    - Calendar for Typescript transcript and carbon copy., 1917.
    - Calendar for Typescript transcript and carbon copy., 1918.
    - Calendar for Typescript transcript and carbon copy., 1919-1920.
    - Dinner appointments and meal guests, Typescript and mimeographed copies., 1927-1932.
    - Calendar for Handwritten original, typescript transcript, carbon copy, and microfilm., 1929.
    - Calendar for Handwritten original, typescript transcript, carbon copy, and microfilm., 1930.
    - Calendar for Handwritten original, typescript transcript, carbon copy, and microfilm., 1931.
    - Calendar for Handwritten original, typescript transcript, carbon copy, and microfilm., 1932. (Box 2)
    - Calendar for Handwritten original, typescript transcript, carbon copy, and microfilm., 1933.
    - Itineraries, Typescript., 1935-1945.
  - Bibliographies, Printed and typescript copies., 1920-1968.
  - Biographical sketches, Printed and typescript copies with related correspondence., 1920-1957.
  - Birthday celebrations, Printed matter, typescripts, and clippings relating to the birthday celebrations for Hoover., 1928-1965.
  - Bookplates, Printed copies., n.d. (Box 3)
  - Calling cards, Printed copies., n.d.
  - Christmas cards, Printed copies., 1911-1962.
  - Christmas celebrations, Typescript and handwritten notes relating to the various Christmas celebrations of the Hoover family., 1958.
  - Club membership cards and passes, Printed copies., 1906-1960.
  - Death of Herbert Hoover.
    - Press reports of illness, Printed copies., 1963.
    - Press releases, Typescripts (carbon copies) and related correspondence., October 18-25, 1964.
    - Eulogies, Printed and typescript copies., 1964-1965.
    - Memorial services at Stanford Memorial Church, Printed and typescript materials relating to the services., 1964.
  - Driver's license, Printed copy., 1926.
  - Homes, Printed matter, typescripts, and telegrams relating to the various homes of the Hoover family., 1920-1971.
    - General.
    - Minthorn House, Newberg, Oregon.
    - Rapidan Camp.
    - Stanford University President's Home. See also Box 369 for San Francisco Chronicle photogravure, 1928.
  - Honors, Printed matter, typescripts, and handwritten notes relating to the recognition of Hoover's career of public service., 1918-1965. (Box 4)
    - General.
    - Degrees, honorary.
    - Hoover Day, Belgium., July 5, 1958
    - Medals.
      - General.
      - Herbert Hoover Medal for Distinguished Service.
    - Schools named after Hoover.
    - Stamps.
      - Commemorative covers, 1965.
      - Commemorative postage stamp, 1965.
  - Marriage license, Certified copy with related printed matter, 1899. 1966.
  - Mining years, Printed matter, typescripts, and photocopies relating to Hoover's activities as a mining engineer., 1897-1965. (Box 5)
    - General.
      - Mining in Australia.
      - Mining in China.
        - General.
        - Chang-Yen Mao suit.
        - Correspondence.
  - Miscellany.
  - Portraits, Printed matter and typescript notes relating to portraits of Hoover., 1944-1966.
  - Signatures, Holographs and printed copies.
  - Stanford diploma, Original document in leather folder., 1895.
  - Stanford years, Printed matter and typescripts relating to Hoover's academic record and campus activities as a student at Stanford University., 1897-1966.